The Life of Muhammadﷺ, Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar_Awlaki,
اَلْحَمْدُ لله رَبِّ الْعلَمِيْن ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِ الْاَنْبِيَاءِ وَلْمُرْسَلِيْن ، مُحَمَّد اِبْنِ عَبْدالله وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
We're carrying on with the Battle of the conquest of Makkah, Fath Makkah(فتح مكه).
We said that Rasool Allah ﷺ left in Ramadan(رمضان),
and when they were close to Makkah, they started breaking their fast by the command of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
they were told not to carry on fasting.
They reached an area called Marr Az-Zahran(مرة أظهران) on their way.
And there were trees of Araak(أراك),
Araak(أراك) is the tree which Miswaak(مسواك) is taken from,
the good Miswaak(مسواك) is the root of this tree,
but also the branches, the tender branches can be used as a Miswaak(مسواك).
So, the tree is called Al-Araak(الاراك) .
There's a tiny fruit for this tree called Al-Kubbaas(ألكباث),
very small, like a pea, but smaller than a pea.
And they're sweet, but they also have that taste of Al-Miswaak(مسواك) in them, and they're edible.
So, the Sahabah(صحابه) were plucking, this Kubbas(الكباث)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ told them to take the black ones because they are the best.
Because it starts out as green and then it turns, I think yellow and red and then and then Black.
So, black is when it's ripe.
Now, Al-Araak(الاراك) doesn't grow in Makkah, it's outside of Makkah.
So, they told Rasool Allah ﷺ, you must have been a shepherd of sheep.
Because it is the shepherd's, who eat Al-Kubbas(الكباث), since it is outside the Makkah,
they're the ones, who usually harvest it, and eat it.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes, and every Nabbi(نبي) has been a shepherd.
Every Nabbi(نبي) has been a shepherd of sheep.
And we talked about the Hikmah(حكمه), the wisdom behind the Ambiyaa(أنبياء) of Allah being shepherds.
We talked about that, in one of the lectures of Makkah.
Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه was climbing.
This is not very high tree, it's like a short tree.
So, Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه was climbing to try to get the Al-Kubbas(الكباث)
and his legs were showing, his shin, they were very, very slim.
So, some of the Sahabah(صحابه) were laughing, at the thinness of his legs.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
You are surprised by the thinness of the shins of Abdullah Bin Masood(عبد الله بن مسعود),
in the name of Allah, they are heavier on the scales, on the Day of Judgment than the mountain of Uhud(أحَد).
So, Abdullah Bin Masood(عبد الله بن مسعود) is going to be very heavy on the scales on the Day of Judgment.
His deeds are very heavy.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ, he gave this Fazilah(فضيلة) to Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه, this virtue.
And when they were walking, suddenly a rabbit jumped.
So, they followed it and one of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم was able to catch the rabbit.
So, they took it to, Abu Talha(ابو طلحه), who slaughtered it
and then they sent a piece of it to Rasool Allah ﷺ, and he ate it.
So, rabbit is Halal(حلال).
Up until that moment, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) had no idea about the movements of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
A huge army of 10,000 strong,
yet Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were blind and deaf concerning the movements of Rasool Ullah.
While whenever, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) would make a movement Rasool Allah ﷺ would be alerted.
So, the intelligence gathering of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Muslims was at a much higher caliber than Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And that is a blessing from Allahعَزّوجَلّ that
he gave the Muslims even though their resources were much less
and the Kuffar(كفار) in the area were much more.
I mean, the number of Muslims, until that moment was quite small,
was limited to Madina and the surrounding areas of Madina, the rest of Arabia were all Kuffar(كفار).
Nevertheless, Rasool Allah ﷺ had disciplined and trained the Sahabah(صحابه) to be alert
and he would send them out scouting for information,
while Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) up until, this moment had no clue about what was going on.
Another reason which made the intelligence gathering of the Muslims better than Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
is the loyalty that, they had to Rasool Allah ﷺ, so information would not leak.
And as we have seen in the case of Hatib Ibn Abi Baltaa رضي الله عنه that was a single case,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was alerted to it, by Al-Wahee(ألوحي).
So, the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم would never disclose information about the movements of the Muslims.
One of the things that we suffer today is the lack of loyalty,
and the lack of understanding of Al-Wala Wal Baraa(ألولآء ولبرآء).
So Muslims who claim to be Muslims are willing not only to give information on a single incident basis,
but are willing to work long term for the Kuffar(كفار) giving them information about the Muslims,
spying against the Muslims, and this is Nifaq(نفاق).
A person, who does so is a Munafiq(منافق).
A person who gives up information about the Muslims, spies in the Masajid(مساجد),
and collects information and delivers it to the Kuffar(كفار).
How will he escape the wrath of Allahعَزّوجَلّ on the day of Judgment?
So, Muslims need to fear Allah, they need to have Taqwa(تقوى)
and they need to have the correct understanding of what Al-Wala Wal Baraa(ألولآء ولبرآء) means.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was in this area of Marr Az-Zahran(مرة أظهران),
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) himself, the leader of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
along with Budail Bin Warqah(بديل بن ورقع) and Hakeem Bin Hizaam(حكيم بن حزام),
they came out of Makkah, searching for information, asking the travelers.
At night they were close to the Muslim army and they saw the lights of the Muslims.
So, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) is saying, who are these?
Budail Bin Warqah(بديل بن ورقع) said: This is Khuza'a(خزاعه) preparing for war.
Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) said: Khuza'a(خزاعه) is much less than this, to have all of these lights.
This cannot be Khuza'a(خزاعه)
اَظلُّ أقل
He said: They are more humble and few, to have these lights.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) and Budail(بديل) and Hakeem(حكيم) were overseeing the Muslim army
but the Muslim guards were alert and they arrested the three of them.
And they took them to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
in one narration, they were arrested and that's a stronger narration.
In another narration, it was Al-Abbas Ibn Abdul Muttalib(العباس اِبن عبد  المطلب), who found them.
Anyway, we'll go with the narration that, they were arrested
so they were taken to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
In one narration it says, that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) saw Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان),
so he wanted to kill him.
But Al-Abbas(العباس) had Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) ride on the mule of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he was rushing to get to Rasool Allah ﷺ before Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) can kill Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان),
until they entered into the place where Rasool Allah ﷺ was
and Umar(عمر) tried to have Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) killed.
While Al-Abbas(العباس) was appealing to Rasool Allah ﷺ to spare his life.
And the argument kept on going on,
Al-Abbas(العباس) is trying to convince Rasool Allah ﷺ to spare his life
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is trying to convince Rasool Allah ﷺ to allow him to be executed.
And then Al-Abbas(العباس) got angry and he said;
O Umar(عمر), if he was one of Bannu Addi(بنوعدي),
Bannu Addi(بنوعدي) are the clan of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) is the tribe and then you have clans.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) belongs to Bannu Addi(بنوعدي),
so Al-Abbas(العباس) is telling Umar(عمر), if he was from amongst the clan of Bannu Addi(بنوعدي),
you wouldn't have said so, but you know that he is from Abdul Manaf(بنوعبد مناف),
Bannu Abd-Manaf(بنوعبد المناف) are the family of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and also the family of Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), they're both descendants of Abd-Manaf(عبد المناف).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) told Al-Abbas(العباس),
مَهْلًا يَا عَبَّاْس
wait, Al-Abbas(العباس)
your Islam is more beloved to me then the Islam of my father Al-Khattab(الخطاب), if he had became Muslim.
Because I know that Rasool Allah ﷺ would become more pleased by the Islam of you,
then if my father has become Muslim.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) is making it clear to Al-Abbas(العباس) that,
this is not how, we Muslims think we don't think on a tribal level.
That's not our way of thinking.
I am more happy for your Islam
because you are the uncle of Rasool Ullah and it is pleasing to Rasool Ullah,
so what pleases me, is what pleases Rasool Ullah
and what makes me angry is what displeases Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) here is giving Al-Abbas Ibn Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبد المطلب) a lesson in how the Muslims think.
We do not view things from a nationalistic view, or family based view, or a clan view, or tribal view.
We based things on Al-Wala Wal Baraa(ألولآء ولبرآء),
if a person is close to Allah, then we are loyal to that person.
If a person is far away from Allah, then we are free and we disassociate ourselves from such a person.
Anyway Rasool Allah ﷺ told them to leave and come back in the morning, according to that narration,
and when they met in the morning,
Rasool Allah ﷺ accepted the Islam of Budail Bin Warqah(بديل بن ورقع) and Hakeem Bin Hizaam(حكيم بن حزام).
To Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
Isn't it about time, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) that you recognize that there is no god but One.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) said, to Rasool Allah ﷺ
مَا اَحْلَمَكَ وَمَا اَكْرَمَكْ
You're merciful and you are generous.
And then, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) said;
If there were any other gods besides Allah,
they would have given us protection and have defended us.
So, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) has accepted that there is no God but Allah.
There is no one worthy of worship but Allah, he accepted that.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told him.
Isn't it about time Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), that you testify that I am the messenger of Allah.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) said: O Rasool Ullah, there's something in my heart against this at the moment.
So, I accept
اَشْهَدُ الله الهَ الَّا الله
but I still feel difficulty accepting that Muhammad(محمد) is the Messenger of Allah.
Al-Abbas(العباس) told him: Woe to you, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان),
become a Muslim before your head is chopped, before you're executed,
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) said;
وَاَشْهَدُ اَنَّ مُحَمَّدَ الرَّسُوْل الله
And he became a Muslim.
Rasool Allah ﷺ gave his instructions to Al-Abbas(العباس) to hold back, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) from leaving
and to have him, wait at the mountain pass.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted Al-Abbas(العباس) to hold back Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) for a reason.
And he wanted him to wait at the mountain pass for a reason.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to demonstrate, to the leader of the Kuffar(كفار), the strength of the Muslims.
When Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) would see, the overwhelming forces
that Rasool Allah ﷺ has brought together, to invade Makkah
that would stop and bring an end to any willingness or desire to resist.
Because even though Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) has become Muslim,
he's a new Muslim and he's a leader of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and he might have some interest there,
and the people in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) might want to fight.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted these people, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) and the ones with him,
to see with their own eyes because hearing something is not like seeing it.
To see with their own eyes, the 10,000 strong army of Rasool Allah ﷺ
because Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want bloodshed in Makkah.
So, he wanted them to see, how strong the Muslims are so that they would just surrender.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has divided the army into battalions, you can see.
And every battalion had a Ra'yah(راية), had the banner.
And they were divided according to their tribes.
So, Bannu Sulaim(بنوسُلَيم), were separate, Ghifaar(غفار) were separate, Muzaina(مزينه)
and they were passing from this mountain pass because it's a narrow area,
they were passing one after the other.
And whenever, one of these battalions would move through the mountain pass,
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) would ask Al-Abbas(العباس). Who are they?
And Al-Abbas(العباس) would tell him, this is the Ghifaar(غفار), Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) would say:
مَا لِيْ وَمَا لِلْغِفَار
I have nothing to do with Ghifaar(غفار).
And then Sulaim(سُلَيْم), I have nothing to do with Sulaim(سُلَيْم),
Muzaina(مزينه), I have nothing to do with Muzaina(مزينه).
Until one battalion passed and it caught the attention of Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان).
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), you can sometimes sense the strength of what you see.
So, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) saw this particular battalion
and it caught his attention and he told Al-Abbas(العباس), who are these.?
Al-Abbas(العباس) told him, these are the Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار).
And the banner of Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار) was with Saad Ibn Ubadah رضي الله عنه,
who was the leader of Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج).
When Sa'ad(سعد) saw, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), he told Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان).
يا أبوسُفِيان اَلْيَوْمْ يَوْمُ الْمَلْحَمَّه، اَلْيَوْمْ تسْتَحَلَ الْكَعْبَهْ
Today is the day of the great battle, today is the day when the sanctuary of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) would be violated.
Saad Ibn Ubadah رضي الله عنه, a great Sahabi(صحابي) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, a leader of Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار),
one of the men, who gave Nusrah(نصرة), victory to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
however at that particular moment, enthusiasm probably led him to speak out and utter these words.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) and Al-Abbas(العباس) and others and even says that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب),
they carried these words of Saad Ibn Ubadah(سَعد اِبن عبادة) to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
كَذَبَ سَعْد
Sa'ad(سعد) lied.
Now, the word, lie here, in this context means, is mistaken.
It doesn't mean literally lie, it means that he is mistaken, Sa'ad(سعد) is mistaken.
كَذَبَ سَعْد، وَلَكِنْ هَذَا يَوْم يُعَظِمُ الله فِيْهَ الْكَعْبَهْ
Sa'ad(سَعد) has lied but this is a day in which Allah, will glorify Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
The sanctity of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) will not be violated.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that the banner be taken away from Saad Ibn Ubadah(سَعد اِبن عبادة)
and be given to his son Qais Bin Saad Ibn Ubada(قيس بن سَعد اِبن عبادة).
This is a for two reasons.
The first reason, Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want Saad Ibn Ubadah(سَعد اِبن عبادة), to have authority
and probably this would lead him into bloodshed into Makkah.
You can see that Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to avoid shedding blood in Makkah.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want the banner to remain in his hands,
but in the same time Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to anger or upset Saad Ibn Ubadah(سَعد اِبن عبادة).
Saad Ibn Ubadah(سَعد اِبن عبادة) is gonna accept the orders of Rasool Ullah, no matter what?
But probably there would be something in his heart, he might be upset that the banner was taken from him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave it, to his own son.
Rasool Allah ﷺ entered peacefully, there was no resistance.
But the area in which Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) came in
there was resistance from Bannu Bakr(بنوبكر) and Hudail(حديل),
Bannu Bakr(بنوبكر) and Hudail(حديل) are tribes that live on the outskirts of Makkah,
they don't live in Makkah itself.
They put up a fight, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) just destroyed them.
So, they, they all just ran away.
They gave up and that was the end of resistance.
Therefore, there's a difference of opinion among the scholars.
هَلْ فُتِحَت الْمَكَةْ صُلْحًا اَمْ عُنْوَةً
Was Makkah opened by force or was it opened through agreement?
What are the implications of this difference of opinion?
The implications are in matters of Fiqh(فقه),
because when a land is opened by force
than everything that belongs to the Kuffar(كفار) turns into the property of Muslims, even themselves.
So, everything on the land and on top of the land becomes property of the Muslims.
If that land was opened by force,
so the population could be enslaved and all of their property could be taken away and split among the Muslims.
This is if, it was opened by force.
However, if it was open, Sulhan(صلحا) , by agreement,
then the Kuffar(كفار) can have some right of ownership
and they are not enslaved and they remain free.
So, there's a difference of opinion among Ulema(علماء) on Fateh Makkah(فتح مكه).
Some scholars say it was opened by force and some of them say it was opened by agreement.
And the implications of this are the reflection of it is regarding the property that exists in Makkah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ entered Makkah.
Now, this is after an absence of eight years.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has left Makkah eight years ago, secretly and there was a plot to kill him.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ had to flee from the danger that existed in Makkah.
Eight years and now Rasool Allah ﷺ is entering Makkah victoriously.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Muhajiroon(مهاجرون) spent 13 years in Makkah suffering,
torture, evil words, boycott, all types of harm that you could imagine the Muslims went through.
And now it's chance for revenge.
It's a chance to slaughter those, who caused all of this punishment and torture and hardship on the Muslims.
It could have been a chance for a great celebrations of victory, as different armies do,
whenever they conquer a new land.
But how did Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Muslims enter Makkah?
Did Rasool Allah ﷺ enter Makkah with mission accomplished, propaganda and celebrations and puffing of champagne bottles as the Kuffar(كفار) do.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ and the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, when they entered into Makkah,
the description that was given of Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he was entering, is that
he entered with humbleness, Khushooh(خشوع), and he was reciting Surah Fateh(سورة فتح).
The Surah(سورة) of conquest and his head was lowered so down
that it could touch the Rahal(رحل) of the camel, his beard was touching it
and he would recite the Ayaat(آيات) and repeat them.
He had the black turban on, and he had a white flag banner,
and he entered into Makkah in a state of humbleness,
thanking Allahعَزّوجَلّ for the conquest, praising Allahعَزّوجَلّ for what He has given him,
Rasool Allah ﷺ then made Tawaaf(طواف) around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and then he called Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه), to bring the key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
The Key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) belonged to Bannu Abd Daar(بنوعبد دار).
Ka'ab(كعب), who's the great grandfather of Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he passed away,
see all of the different honors of Makkah, were in his hand
and then they were split among his children.
So, the family of Rasool Allah ﷺ had the responsibility of providing water to the Hajjaj(حجاج).
The well Zamzam(زمزم), they would provide the Hajjaj(حجاج) with water and that is called Sikaya(سقاية),
and then the family have Bannu Abd Daar(بنوعبد دار),
they were the custodians of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), they held on to the key, so the key was with them.
Uthman(عثمان) was a Muslim and Rasool Allah ﷺ told him to go and get the key,
the key was with his mother.
So, he went in the beginning, she refused and then he took the key.
And he brought it to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), and he entered
and he saw a pigeon made out of wood, he destroyed it.
There were images on the walls of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) of angels and Ibrahim عليه السّلام,
using Istasqaam Bil Izlaam(إستسقام بلإزلام) which is the dividing arrows,
which is one of the Bid'ah(بدعة) of Jahilliya(جاهلية).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قَاتَلَهُمُ الله
May Allah Kill them.
They portrayed our elder, meaning our grandfather, Ibrahim(ابراهيم),
as using these divining arrows.
And then he ordered Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) to wipe out all of these images from inside the Ka'aba(كعبه),
so Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), soaked a cloth in water and then wiped out all of these images.
So, when Rasool Allah ﷺ entered in Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), it was clean
from all of the innovations of Jahilliya(جاهلية) and Kuffr(كفر).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ came out from Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) and he stood on the door of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), which was high,
and by now all of the people were gathering around him.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ spoke to the crowd.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they all came out now to listen to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Let's go back a few years when Rasool Allah ﷺ received the initial revelation from Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and was commanded to, deliver the warning to his people,
وَأَنْذِرْ عَشِيرَتَكَ الْأَقْرَبِينَ
Warn your close relatives or your clan, that was in the beginning.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ stood on a mountain in Makkah, and he said;
وَا صُباحَاه
And this is the call to make when there is an emergency situation,
you don't just say Wa'sabahaa(وا صباحاه) for nothing,
you say it when there's something very urgent
because everybody is going to respond, it's a serious call.
So all of the people came and those, who could not come sent a representative to listen.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
إنِّي نَذِيرٌ لَكُمْ بيْنَ يَدَيْ عَذَابٌ اَلِيْمْ
I'm delivering a warning to you, before a severe punishment will befall you.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said this, Abu Lahab(ابولهب) said;
تَبًّا لَكْ ألهَذَا دَعَوْتَنَا
May you be cut off, is this why you have summoned us?
Abu Lahab(ابولهب) was buying and selling, a businessman
and he left his shop and he came to listen to what Rasool Allah ﷺ had to say.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ had this message to deliver to them,
he was upset and angry and the crowds left and from that time on,
no one wants to listen to  what, Rasool Allah ﷺ has to say.
And imagine how difficult it is, to deliver Da'wah(دعوة) to people who don't want to listen.
But now, since Rasool Allah ﷺ is leading an army,
now since Rasool Allah ﷺ has strength,
and since he is the head of state, everybody came voluntarily to listen.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not call anyone
by the time Rasool Allah ﷺ came out and turned this back and face the people.
All of the people of Makkah were under him listening to what Rasool Allah ﷺ has to say and watching his every move,
because, when Rasool Allah ﷺ went to the well of Zamzam(زمزم), to drink from it and to make Wudhu(وضؤ).
The Sahabah(صحابه) were rushing to grab the water that would drip from his body,
and then they would wipe it over their skin.
So, the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were saying: We have never seen such a king before.
Now, they're watching every single movement of Rasool Ullah and they're reporting it,
that's how we knew about this incident.
It is because they reported it, to us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ now, is the same Rasool Allah ﷺ then,
but in the beginning because Rasool Allah ﷺ did not have strength.
No one wanted to listen to what Rasool Allah ﷺ has to say.
But now, it is different.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ delivered a short speech from the door of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدالله), Praise be to Allah, Who has fulfilled His promise.
صَدَقَه وَعْدَه  ونصره عبده
And He has helped His servent.
وَهَزَمَ الأَحْزَابَ وَحْدَةْ
And He has defeated the opposing parties alone.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ is instituting some new laws in Makkah,
compensation for those killed by kwazii intent by whip or cudgel shall be compensated by 100 camels,
this is Diyat Shib Al-Amd(دِيْة شِبْه أَلْعَمْدَ).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them all privilege of ancestry and pride that existed in the Jahilliya(جاهلية) are finished.
Listen to this statement;
All privilege of ancestry and pride that existed in the Jahilliya(جاهلية) are finished.
These are the foundations of the Society of Jahilliya(جاهلية).
The foundation, the Constitution, the laws, the customs of the Arabs of Jahilliya(جاهلية) were based on this,
privilege of ancestry and pride.
In this one statement,
Rasool Allah ﷺ is bringing a new era, and he's telling the people who are listening under his feet, he's telling him;
That the time of Jahilliya(جاهلية), the rules of Jahilliya(جاهلية), the customs of Jahilliya(جاهلية),
are all behind your backs now, they are all finished.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is bringing a new era,
Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling the Kuffar(كفار), that Kuffr(كفر) is over with.
I'm not going to accommodate you, I'm not going to accept your laws,
I'm not going to accept your customs and ways, it's all finished.
In another narration Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Both these factors meaning ancestry and pride are beneath these feet of mine.
They're under my feet, they're over with.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not try to win over the hearts of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
by accepting some of the rules and customs.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) would fight for their customers, they would die for their customs,
who fought against Rasool Allah ﷺ for 20 years
for no purpose other than the purpose of protecting the old way.
They were not religious people by the way.
Ya'ani(يعني) even though, they had 360 idols surrounding Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
they were not known to be religious people.
But it was the status quo that they were trying to protect.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not try to win them over by accepting some of Al-Jahilliya(ألجاهلية).
Rasool Allah ﷺ in his first speech delivered in Makkah, made it clear that your ways are under my feet.
Now, the key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) is in the hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), from the family of Bannu Hashim(بنوهاشم),
he told Rasool Allah ﷺ;
يَا رَسول الله، اِجْمَعْ لَنَا بَيْنَ سِقَايَة وَالْحِجَابَة
O Rasool Ullah combined for us the honors of providing the pilgrims with water
and holding on to the key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ do?
And by the way, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) said, this because it was a great opportunity.
These were very important things to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
I mean, holding onto the key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) was such a great honor.
In fact, that is what gave Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) this prestige, among all of the Arabs
it was because they were custodians of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was trying to convince Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he took this opportunity and told Rasool Ullah;
How about we combined for us for our family, the honor of holding onto the Key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)?
It's in your hands right now.
Rasool Allah ﷺ called Uthman(عثمان) and he gave him the key, and they told him.
خُذُوهَا خَالِدَةً مُخَلِّدَةً لَا يَاخُذْهَا مِنْكُمْ إِلَّا ظَالِمٌ
Take it forever, and no one will take it from you but an oppressor,
no one will take it from you but the tyrant
and that is why the key of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) still exists among the descendants of Uthman Ibn Talha(عثمان ابن طلحه), until this day,
and they are called Bannu Shaibah(بنوشيبة).
The key has been passing on from father to son until, this day.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ riding on his camel, was going around Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
in one narration holding on to a stick and the other narration holding on to his bow,
and he was pointing towards these idols, these glorified idols, these sacred idols, to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
and they're all watching and Rasool Allah ﷺ is going around, and he's poking these idols in their eyes.
And in one narration, he was just pointing towards the idols,
and they were falling one after the other.
If he points towards the face of the idol, it would fall back on its back,
and if Rasool Allah ﷺ points towards the back of the idol, it would fall on, on his face.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ did that with the 360 idols surrounding Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and all of the Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are watching this monumental moment,
when all of their gods that have been there for centuries and centuries,
they're watching their idols falling down breaking into pieces.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was saying;
وَقُلْ جَاءَ الْحَقُّ وَزَهَقَ الْبَاطِلُ ۚ إِنَّ الْبَاطِلَ كَانَ زَهُوقًا
Rasool Allah ﷺ was reciting, this Ayah(آية), the truth has come, and error has gone.
Error is bound to disappear, error or evil is bound to disappear
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ told the people Quraish(قُرَيْشْ);
مَا تَظُنُّوْنَ أَنِّي فَاعِلٌ بِكُمْ؟
What do you think I will do to you?
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they said: What they believe is the case with Muhammadﷺ
they know him.
قَالُوا: أَخٌ كَرِيمٌ، وَابْنُ أَخٍ كَرِيمٍ،
They said: You are a noble brother and the son of a noble brother.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
اِذْهَبُوا فَأَنْتُمْ الطُّلَقَاءُ
Go! You are the freed ones.
You are a Tulaqa'a(طلقاء), You are freed because you are in my hands.
And I could, by a point of my finger by just waving my hand,
I could order all of you to be executed.
And that would happen, if I wanted to happen.
But he told them you are free.
And that's why the people who became Muslim, at the conquest of Makkah are called At-Tulaqa'a(اَطُّلقاء), the freed ones
because Rasool Allah ﷺ is the one, who freed them, he released them.
You are the released ones, probably the word released is more accurate.
You are the released ones.
اِذْهَبُوا فَأَنْتُمْ الطُّلَقَاءُ
Go! You are the released ones.
Rasool Allah ﷺ released them all but there was a blacklist.
There were exceptions,
this blacklist included the names of Abdullah bin Khattl(عبدالله بن خطل),
Abdullah Bin Abi Sar'h(عبدالله بن ابي ألسرح), Maqees Bin Sababah(مقيس بن صبابة),
Al-Huwairis Bin Naqeez(الحويرث بن نقيذ) and Sarah(سارة), Fartana(فرتنى) and Arnub(ارنب).
So, there were four men and three women, Rasool Allah ﷺ said, about these,
اُقْتُلُوْهُمْ وَلو وَجَدْتُمُوْهُمْ مُعَلَقِيْنَ بِأَسْتَارِ الْكَعْبَةِ
Execute them, even if you see them, hanging on to the clothes of Al-Ka'aba(الكعبه).
Why were these excluded from the rest of the people of Makkah?
With Abdullah Bin Khattl(عبدالله بن خطل), he became Muslim, he made Hijra(هجرة)
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ sent him to collect Sadaqah(صدقه), charity.
On the way, Ya'ani(يعني) he was sent with a man from Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار) and then he had a servant, a slave
on the way he was upset with his servant,
it says in one narration, that he ordered the servant to prepare lunch.
And when it was time for lunch, he told him, where's the lunch the servant told them I forgot.
So, he killed him.
Now, he knew that is going to be punished for this,
Rasool Allah ﷺ was not gonna let him go, in Islam, there's justice,
whether you are a slave or a noble man, the law of Allah will apply to you.
So, Abdullah Bin Khattl(عبدالله بن خطل), knew this in advance.
He therefore, decided to run away to Makkah and he committed apostasy.
And he had two slave girls, whom he would teach to sing against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Abdullah bin Khattl(عبدالله بن خطل), he was excluded because of his Riddah(ردة)
and because of his blasphemy against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And his two slave girls, singers Fartana(فرتنى) and Arnub(ارنب).
They were included on the list because of their blasphemy against Rasool Allah ﷺ, cursing Rasool Ullah.
Abdullah Bin Abi Sar'h(عبدالله بن ابي السرح), he became Muslim
and he would write Qur'an for Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Allah ﷺ had scribes, he would recite the Ayaat(آيات) to them
and they would write them down.
Abdullah Bin Abi Sar'h(عبدالله بن ابي سرح), he then ran away and he became a Murtadd(مرتد), he became an apostate.
And he went as far as telling the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
that I would change Qur'an, when I would write it down,
I would change the meanings of Qur'an.
Maqees Bin Sababah(مقيس بن صبابة),
Maqees Bin Sababah(مقيس بن صبابة), his brother was a Muslim in the Battle of Bannu Al-Mustallaq(بنوالمصطلق),
he was killed by mistake he was killed by mistake by a man from Al-Ansaar(الانصار).
So, Maqees(مقيس), he made Hijrah(هجرة) and he became Muslim.
Just to collect the money, the blood money of his brother.
So, Rasool Ullah paid him the money.
After he received the money he ran away and became a Murtadd(مرتد).
Al-Huwairis Bin Naqeez(الحويرس بن نقيظ);
When Al-Abbas Ibn Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبد المطلب) sent Fatima(فاطمه) and Zainab(زينب), the daughters of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Madina.
Al-Huwairis(الحويرث), he provoked the camel, which Zainab(زينب) and Fatimah(فاطمه) were on,
and that led to both of them falling.
And Zainab(زينب) having a miscarriage.
The daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ had a miscarriage because of the actions of this man, Al-Huwairis(الحويرث).
Sarah(سارة) was a slave girl, that belonged to someone in Makkah,
and she used to sing against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, we can see that everyone on this blacklist
was excluded from the forgiveness of Rasool Allah ﷺ
for one, of two reasons,
either because they have committed Riddah(ردا), apostasy or because of blasphemy.
These are the two things that are unforgiven, Riddah(ردة)
and speaking in an insulting way, against Rasool Allah ﷺ there's no forgiveness for both of these two crimes.
And that's why Ibn Taymiyyah(إبن تيميه) says;
That the rules concerning Riddah(ردة), apostasy are more strict than the rules, concerning Kuffr(كفر).
One example a kafir(كافر) who is prisoner of war, the Imam(امام) has a right to execute him,
or to free him, or to ask for ransom, or to exchange him with Muslim prisoners of war or to enslave him.
It is up to the Imam(امام) to choose one of these options.
However, with the Murtadd(مرتد),
Ibn Taymiyyah(إبن تيميه) says; There's only one option and that is to be executed.
A Murtadd(مرتد) prisoner of war
cannot be freed, cannot be enslaved, cannot be exchanged, he can only be executed,
or if he becomes Muslim, then he is freed.
But if he refuses, then there's only have the option of execution.
That's one example of how the rulings concerning apostasy are different than the rulings concerning Kuffr(كفر).
Abdullah bin Khattl(عبدالله بن خطل) was seen hanging on to the clothes of Al-Ka'aba(الكعبه)
and he was executed on the spot.
Some narrations say that Fartana(فرطنى) was killed
while Arnub(ارنب) she became Muslim and she was forgiven.
Abdullah Bin Abi Sar'h(عبدالله بن ابي سرح), he sought refuge with his brother from breastfeeding Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان), Akhoo Min-Ar-Ridha(أخوه من الرضاعة)
Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) took, Abdullah Bin Abi Sar'h(عبدالله بن ابي سرح) to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Abdullah Bin Abi Sar'h(عبدالله بن ابي سرح) said;
I came to give you a Baiyah(بيعة), Rasool Ullah was quite,
he said: I came to give you Baiyah(بيعة) Rasool Ullah did not respond.
The third time he said: I came to give you Baiyah(بيعة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ accepted his Baiyah(بيعة).
And then when he left, Rasool Allah ﷺ told the men, who were there.
Is there no wise men among you, who could have got up and killed him?
When you saw I was remaining silent.
So, the Ansaar(انصار) said: But O Rasool Ullah could you not have given us some signal?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَا يَنْبَغِيْ لِنَبِيٍّ اَنْ يَقْتُلَ بِالْاِشَارَةْ
Prophets do not kill by making signals.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: It's not appropriate for me, as a prophet to give you a signal.
You already knew my Hukum(حكم) my ruling concerning him, so you could have killed him.
It says in one narration that one of the Ansaar(انصار) already had his hand on the sword.
He was ready to execute the man but he was waiting for a signal from Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), that was the Qadar(قدر) of Allah to spare the life of Abdullah Bin Abi Sar'h(عبدالله بن ابي سرح),
because he became a good Muslim after that.
In fact, it says that he died in Sujood(سجود) of Salat Ul Fajr(صلاةالفجر)
and he held some very high positions of authority in the times of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) and Uthman(عثمان).
Maqees Bin Sababah(مقيس بن صبابه) was killed by his cousin,
Al-Huwairis Bin Naqeez(الحويرث بن نقيذ) was also killed.
Sarah(سارة) some say that she was forgiven.
So, we can see the important ruling here of the Hukum(حكم) of Sabb(صب) of Rasool Allah ﷺ do.
The ruling of committing blasphemy against Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Umma Haana(اُمّ هاني) is the sister of Ali Ibn Abi Talib,  رضي الله عنهم اجمعين,
two her in laws, sought refuge with her.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) came in and said: I will kill them,
Umma Haana(اُمّ هاني) had them hide in her place and then she went to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
who was bathing and Fatimah رضي الله عنه was screening him.
and he was bathing from out of the container that's still had marks of dough in it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ welcomed her and greeted her and said: What has brought you.?
He greeted her very well and then he said: What has brought you.?
She said: The son of my mother,
has said that he will kill the two men that I have given protection.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
أَجَرْنَا مَنْ أَجَرْتِ يَا أمَّ هَانَئ
We give protection to the ones, you have given protection, Umma Haana(اُمّ هاني).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ approved her protection, and he has spared the lives of her two in laws.
And Umma Haana(اُمّ هاني) saw Rasool Allah ﷺ pray eight Raka'at(ركعات),
every two Raka'a(ركعة) were separate.
So, the scholars had the difference of opinion.
Or these are Salaat-Uz-Zuhaa(صلاة الضحى) or are they the Salah(صلاة) of conquest.
Some of them said: It is the (صلاة) of conquest,
because no one has reported them except Umma Haana(اُمّ هاني) in this particular day, which was the day of the opening of Makkah.
While some of them say
that they are Salaat Uz Zuhaa(صلاة الضحى) because in the narration it says
that he prayed them in the time of the Dhuhaa(الضحى).
Abu Qahafah(ابوقحافة), the Father of Abu Bakr(ابو بكر).
He told his youngest daughter to take him on top of the mountain of Abu Qubais(ابوقبيس).
This is a mountain in Makkah.
And his sight was very weak.
So, she took him on top of the mountain.
He told her: O daughter describe to me what you see?
She said;
اِنِّيْ اَرَآء سَوَادً
I see a black mass.
He told her, those are the horsemen and then he told her what do you see?
she said: I see a man going back and fro.
So, Abu Qahafah(ابوقحافة) said;
ذَالِكَ الْوَازَة
That is the man, who gives instructions to the cavalry.
And then she said: I see the black mass dispersing.
He said: The orders have been given to the cavalry. Let's rush back.
But they didn't get home on time, they met the cavalry on their way.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), one of the soldiers saw a silver necklace on the neck of the Daughter of Abu Qahafah(ابوقحافة).
So, he ripped it apart from her neck.
Abu Bakr رضي الله عنه went to his father and he brought him to meet Rasool Ullah.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ saw the old man.
Rasool Ullah told Abu Bakr(ابو بكر);
هَلَّا تَرَكْتَ الشَيْخْ فَاَكُوْنُ اَنَا الَّذِيْ آتِيْكْ
Why didn't you leave the Shaikh(شيخ),
Shaikh(شيخ) means old man at home,
so that I would be the one, who would come to him. Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said;
هُوَ اَحَقّ اَنْ يَمْشِيْ اَلَيْكْ مِنْ اَنْ تَمْشِيَّ اَنْتَ اِلَيْه
It is more fitting for him to come to you rather than you go to him.
So, this shows you the respect that Rasool Allah ﷺ had for Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) in offering to go and visit his father.
And you can see the respect, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) had for Rasool Allah ﷺ,
telling Rasool Ullah that my father should come to you, not you go to him.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ put his hand on the chest of Abu Qahafah(ابوقحافة).
And he wiped his chest and said: Aslim(أسْلِم) so he became Muslim.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told them: To change the color of his hair because
his hair was described as being like Sughama(ثغامة),
Sughama(ثغامة) is a white bird.
So, all of his hair was gray, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
غَيَّرُه’ وَلَا تُقَرِّبُوْه’ السوَادْ
change the color of his hair, but don't make it black.
Therefore, the Ulema(علماء) have derived the ruling that the old man should not dye his hair black,
but you change it to a different color and that is the color of Hinnah(حنا), which is red.
And some scholars said, that if a person is young, then they can dye their hair black.
But if they are at the age, which is natural for them to have gray hair,
they shouldn't dye it black, but they should dye it with Hinnah(حنا).
The daughter of Abu Qahafah(ابو قحافة), the sister of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
she told her brother, that her necklace was taken away.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said;
اَيُّهَاالنَّاس
O people, has anyone taken the necklace of my sister, no one responded.
So he said;
إِحتَسِبِيْ
He told her to seek the Ajr(أجر) of it from Allah.
إِحتَسِبِيْ يَا بُنَيَّ فَاِنَّ الْاَمَانَة فِيْ النَّاسِ يَوْمَ قَلِيْلْ
Because trust is little in the people today.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) comments on this and says;
The reason why Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said this is because the army was large.
And Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) he is finding an excuse for whoever took the necklace.
He said: Probably he took it considering that it belongs to the people of war.
So, what belongs to them is Ghaneemah(غنيمة)
and he's also given excuse to Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
when he said that the trust today is very rare among the people,
meaning that particular day and not in that era or time,
that particular day because it's a large army, and things could get out of hand,
when an army enters into a town and you have a lot of soldiers.
These are things that happened with armies.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was referring to that particular day
and was not referring to the people in general.
In Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري) it says that Usama Bin Zaid(اسامه بن زيد) asked Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
اَيْنَ الْمَنْزِل غَدًا
Where are you going to spend the night?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
وَهَلْ تَرَكَ لَنَا عَقِيْلٌ مِنْ الرَّبَا
Did Aqeel(عقيل) leave for us any property?
Aqeel(عقيل) has taken over all of the inheritance.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ had nothing left, and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لَا يَرِثُ الْمُؤمِن الْكَافِر وَالْكَافِرِ الْمُؤمِنْ
The believer does not inherit from the disbelievers
and the disbelievers does not inherit from the believer.
And this is the Hukum(حكم) and ruling regarding inheritance.
There is no inheritance between two different religions.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said and this is in Bukhari(البخاري);
مَنْزِلُنَا غَدً اِنْ شَاءَالله بِخَيْفِ بَنِيْ كَنَانَهْ حَيْثُ تَقَاسَمُ عَلَى اَلْكُفْرْ
Tomorrow we're going to stay we're going to spend the night
In Sha Allah(انشاءالله) by the will of Allah in Khaef Bani Kananah(خيف بني كنانة),
place where they have vowed on disbelief.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to replace the Kuffr(كفر) that happened in that place
by spending the night there and reviving the spirit of Eeman(ايمان)
or bringing the spirit of Eeman(ايمان) into that place.
So, if evil happened in that place, he will bring good to it.
These are some events that happened during Fateh Makkah(فتح مكه).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًاكَثِيْرَا
وَالسلا م عليكم ورحمة الله  وبركاته